Guide to the Gifford family papers,1811-1857.
Gifford family papers,1811-1857
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gifford family papers, 1811-1857.
6028
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Twenty seven letters, most addressed to Rowland S. Gifford from relatives and friends discussing a cholera epidemic in Albany, family news, the annexation of Texas, the dissolution of the Union, winter shipping on canals, land speculation, farming and buying a farm. Also miscellaneous legal documents including deeds, affidavits and a receipt.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Two items, 1811-1857. Item 1 contains 26 letters addressed to Rowland S. Gifford covering years 1833-1857. one letter to Merritt J. Cornell from Rowland S. Gif ford, and 4 legal documents (see below). Most of the letters are addressed to Rowland S. Gifford from Henry and Carolin Jones regarding their search for a farm near their aunt and uncle, the Giffords. Others are Arom Merritt J. Cornell, [B.] Conant, Philander Gifford (Rowland's brother), Jesse and Irene Gifford (Irene is presumably Rowland's mother), and J.W. and Polly Pritt. Letters are from Chatham and North Chatham, Valatie, New York, Maiden Bridge, Wilton, and Phelps, all in New York State. Item two is a deed (1811) for Lot no. 53, part of Township no. 11 (Phelps, Ontario County), sold by Sir Johnstone to Robert Rhea. Annexation of Texas (#20), Civil War (#31).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Gifford family.; Gifford, Rowland S.
Subjects:
Family--New York (State); Cholera--New York (State)--Albany.; Canals--New York (State); Farm life--New York (State)--Chatham.
Places:
Texas--Annexation to the United States.; New York (State)--Social life and customs.; Wayne County (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Deeds.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Rowland S. Gifford Letters, Item 1
  - Bill of sale, March 13, 1833, Letter 1
    Aaron C. Gifford and Sylvester W. Conant for sale of Conant's farm in Wilton, Saratoga County, N.Y. Witnessed by two others, one is Rowland S. Gifford.
  - Deed, May 2, 1831., Letter 2
    William Baker to Rowland S. Gifford for part of Lot #11, Wilton, Saratoga County, N.Y.
  - Statement, May 3, 1831, Letter 3
    by Commissioner of Saratoga County that Anna, widow of William Baker, is legally able to sell her deceased husband's land.
  - Irene Gifford (?) to Rowland, Cady, Betsey and Mahala. [April 1833]., Letter 4
    Talk of cholera.
  - Irene Gifford (?) to Mahala and Betsey. A ugust 17, 1834., Letter 5
    More cholera news.
  - Irene Gifford (Chatham, N.Y.) to Rowland S. and Aaron C. Gifford. March 9, 1835., Letter 6
    Family news, health, etc.
  - Jesse and Irene Gifford (North Chatham, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. August 28, 1835., Letter 7
    Bridge accident involving travelling family members.
  - Merritt J. Cornell (Wilton, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. September 6, 1836., Letter 8
    Gifford family moves to Newark or Phelps area.
  - Rowland S. Gifford (Phelps, N.Y.) to Merritt J. Cornell. October 26, 1836., Letter 9
    Copy of reply to previous letter.
  - Merritt J. Cornell (Wilton, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. December 28, 1836., Letter 10
    Reply to previous letter N.B. Letters #'s 8, 9, and 10 concern the sale, bond, and mortgage of Rowland S. Gifford's new home in Phelps. Merritt Cornell is transacting the business.
  - Henry and Carolin Jones (Valatie, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. September 10, 1843., Letter 11
    Jones' plan to buy a farm near the Giffords in Phelps, and a trip to New York City.
  - Henry and Carolin Jones (New York, N.Y.) to Rowland S. and Mahala Gifford. March 24, 1844., Letter 12
    News of the Jones' travels.
  - Henry Jones (New York, N.Y.) to Rowland S. and Mahala Gifford. May 21, 1844., Letter 13
    Reply to a letter from the Giffords.
  - [B.] Conant (Valatie, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. October 25, 1844., Letter 14
    Business and family news. #6028
  - Henry Jones (New York, N.Y.) to Rowland S. and Mahala Gifford. February 24, 1845., Letter 15
    Requests that the Giffords send furniture and belongings.
  - Carolin Jones (New York, N.Y.) to Rowland S. and Mahala Gifford. February [?], 1845., Letter 16
    Same as above.
  - Henry Jones (New York, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. March 26, 1845., Letter 17
    More talk of furniture and moving plans.
  - Philander S. Gifford (Chatham, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. August 10, 1845., Letter 18
    Almost entirely illegible. Talk of a dry season and poor crops.
  - Jesse Gifford (Chatham, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. August 29, 1845., Letter 19
    Dry season; poor crops expected; stock expected to die due to lack of winter grains for feed.
  - B. Conant (Valatie, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. November 18, 1844., Letter 20
    Mentions Polk and the proposed annexation of Texas, the implications for North and South.
  - Henry and Carolin Jones (Valatie, N.Y.) to Rowland S. and Mahala Gifford. November l6, 1844., Letter 21
    Winter shipping on canals, moving to Nassau, looking for land.
  - [B.] Conant (Valatie, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. December 26, 1845., Letter 22
    Re: payments, land speculation.
  - [B.] Conant (Valatie, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. January 14, 1846., Letter 23
    Looking for a farm near Newark.
  - Henry Jones (Valatie, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. January 2, 1846., Letter 24
    Shipping furniture on canals.
  - Philander S. Gifford (Chatham, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. January 12, 1846., Letter 25
    Prices of grain, wheat, flour, oats, corn.
  - [B.] Conant (Valatie, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. February 9, 1346., Letter 26
    Prices of land, the coming of the railroad.
  - Affidavit. [n.d.], Letter 27
    Rowland S. Gifford released from serving jury duty because of deafness.
  - Henry Jones (Newark, N.Y.) to Rowland S. and Mahala Gifford. August 14, 1849., Letter 28
    Carolin's death.
  - Philander S. Gifford (Chatham, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. May 15, 1853., Letter 29
    World's Fair mentioned.
  - Philander S. Gifford (Chatham, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. January 5, 1857, Letter 30
    Asks for money.
  - Polly Pritt (Maiden Bridge, N.Y.) to Rowland S. Gifford. n.d., Letter 31
    Discusses cholera in Albany, from J.W. Pritt mentions Martin Van Buren in New York; a political dispute over tariffs, dissolution of the Union; Henry Clay mentioned as the compromiser.
- Phelps Deed, Item 2
  - Deed, May 14, 1811
    Sale of 132 acres in Phelps, Ontario County, Lot #53, part of township #11. Sir Johnstone to Robert Rhea.